The situation was very heartbreaking.
People were there with signs and they
were just crying and you know asking God
to um help Charlie. And what said about
this is that I already knew that he was
dead. I just I just couldn't bring
myself to tell them that he's already
gone. So they were asking for God to
save him uh for a miracle and I just
couldn't tell him that he was gone.
Hi, I'm John Kuryaku and welcome back to
Deep Focus. A series of new polls
released today and compiled by Stanford
University's Center for the Study of
Extremism says that 34% of college
students say that violence is justified,
violence is justified to silence speech
that they don't agree with. That's up
from 20% just 3 years ago. The number is
astounding, especially in light of
yesterday's grizzly assassination of
Turning Point USA founder and
conservative activist Charlie Kirk. Kirk
was speaking at Utah Valley University
and was just minutes into the event when
he was shot apparently by a man with a
306 mouser rifle. Police have no idea
yet who committed this crime, but the
information released so far is that the
shooter was likely a college-aged man
and was perched on the roof of a closed
building about 200 yards from Kirk. Now,
remember, Kirk was not a moving target.
He was sitting in a chair uh on a stage
and so uh this was a shot that a lot of
people could make, especially if they
had experience hunting. We also know at
this point that police have recovered
what they believe is the rifle used in
the crime and the gun has handprints,
palm prints, and what appears to be
sweat from the gunman's cheek where he
held the gun up. That sweat includes
DNA.
Charlie Kirk's murder has shocked the
political right-wing in the United
States.
It's not unusual for people on the left
or for people who are baby boomers of
baby boomer age not to really know who
Charlie Kirk is. But if you are between
the ages of 16 and 30 and especially if
you are conservative or Republican,
Charlie Kirk was a god, a god in the
movement. Uh I've heard him just in the
last uh 24 hours described as a Martin
Luther King type figure for
conservatives between the ages of 17 and
30. I think that's probably true.
I disagreed with probably 90% of what
Charlie Kirk said, but I respected his
his right to say it. And we can
and we should never blame the victim. Uh
when I was in college, my freshman year,
the first week of freshman year, we had
Abby Hoffman come to campus. Abby Abby
Hoffman was a was an important uh hippie
in the 60s and 70s. He had been arrested
a million times and and was famous
across the country.
Um the college Republicans realized that
those of us in the college Democrats who
had who had requested uh this speech uh
they thought they would uh come and see
what it was all about and they did and
they sat there respectfully and then at
the end the Republicans had questions,
the Democrats had questions and Abby
Hoffman answered them all. Nobody pulled
out a gun and shot him in the neck.
We've really moved far away from where
we used to be in this country. I'm not
saying it's always been great. 1968 was
a year of murder. Martin Luther King was
assassinated in April. Robert Kennedy
was assassinated in in June. People were
in the streets. Killing was taking place
all all over the country. There were
riots in almost all major cities after
Martin Luther King was killed. It was
bad.
But it got better until it didn't. And
now we're in a place where you've got
Fox News on the right, MSNBC on the
left, and the two shall never meet.
Well, we're going to talk about this
with Elizabeth Lane. I had the chance to
interview Elizabeth earlier today. She's
a well-known investigative journalist.
She's a television producer and
documentary filmmaker. and she happened
to be in the hospital in Orin, Utah when
Charlie Kirk died yesterday. Elizabeth,
I want to begin with this horrific
attack on Charlie Kirk yesterday. I I
have a very strong stomach. I've served
for years in war zones over the years
and and I came out of that without any
PTSD, but the graphic attack on Charlie
Kirk has left me deeply unsettled. You
were at the hospital yesterday when he
died. tell us about that. What what
happened? What what was it like and what
was your experience there? It had to be
surreal.
>> Absolutely. And John, um I want to start
with, you know, it's been 24 years since
911 and we still don't have questions.
It's funny that today is 911 and we are
here talking about Charlie Cork's
killing and you know um with this
mysterious circumstances of a sniper and
FBI releasing two witnesses and so on.
I'll tell you what happened at the
hospital when I showed up. What I saw
there first and foremost were people who
were absolutely disillusioned like they
they they were just done with with
everything with government with
everything. They were angry. They had
science. They were praying. They It It
was It was a very
heartbreaking scene. And I'll I'll talk
about the statistics of it too, like
what happened and what should have
happened that didn't happen. But what
really got me was like this people's
reaction to how they kind of accepted
this fact that the government is going
to lie to them. Um and there's nothing
they can do. And you know it's just it's
just a thing now like we have
assassination attempt after
assassination attempt um and we just
roll with it and we don't know anything
about crooks. It's okay right like this
the nation we have become now. So um to
tell you about what happened with the
hospital. So my producer alerted me
about this whole thing as soon as it
happened when Charlie got shot. I got a
text message right away that uh Charlie
got shot in Utah. So the first thing I
did, I got in my car and I started
driving. I didn't know what condition he
was in. Um I was getting my information
on a fly. I was texting other
journalists as well. Um I was asking if
they are going to show up there so I
could get more info. As soon as I showed
up, I saw ton of cops. Um and the whole
hospital was well I shouldn't say under
lockdown, but they wouldn't let me in
from the main entrance. The security
staff of the hospital stopped us right
there. Um, I told them, "Hey, I'm a
journalist. I want to know how Charlie
is. I'm trying to get the information."
They told us that we are not giving out
any information and you guys can stand
in that spot. Like showed us what spot
was designated for the journalists and
they sent us there. They told us that
they would do a conference for us and
tell us what's going on and update us
with the situation. 45 minutes we
waited. No one came in with any info. No
one bothered to do a conference. Nation
was waiting. No one said anything.
So, I started kind of getting stuff, you
know, on my own. Um, I started walking
up to police officers. I knew that
Charlie was there for because one of the
police officers actually confirmed uh
that he was taken in the hospital, but I
didn't know if he was dead or not. And
um I found out from a friend of mine who
had direct information from the hospital
that he had passed. Um, and this is like
somewhere around 10 minutes after I
showed up after I showed up. And then I
had to wait for 45 minutes for people to
come to us and tell us that we've got
nothing for you guys. You can keep
shooting, you know, in in like shooting
the hospital in the situation, but we're
not going to make a conference and there
will be no uh information for you. So
after that, we kind of dug in our own uh
we tried to investigate as much as we
could, but the situation was very
heartbreaking. people were there with
signs and they were just crying and you
know asking God to um help Charlie and
what's said about this is that I already
knew that he was dead. I just I just
couldn't bring myself to tell them that
he's already gone. So they were asking
for God to save him uh for a miracle and
I just couldn't tell him that he was
gone.
As I said in the introduction, the
Stanford University Center for the Study
of Extremism came out with a poll today
that confirmed four previous polls. All
of which found, get this, that 34%
of college students say that violence is
justified to silence speech that they
don't agree with. That's up from 20% 3
years ago. I'm I'm stunned by these
numbers and I'm deeply worried about
them. Universities supposed to be
bastions of free speech and now there's
a sizable minority fully a third o of
all college students who think it's
perfectly okay to murder somebody
because you disagree with them. How do
you think we got to this point? And and
and how do we get back to mutual
respect? Well, getting back to mutual
respect would be really hard because we
conditioned new generation that we told
them this lie that if you're different,
if you are a slightly awkward or if
you're transgender or if you're you know
what you're suppressed, your voice is
suppressed.
>> Yeah. So obviously they are trying to
retaliate and you know everyone would
when they are conditioned into believing
that somehow they have less rights or we
are suppressing their rights if they are
not out there with the flags and
screaming at us how gay they are or how
you know non-binary they are or so on.
So we created this situation where we
put these ideas in their head that they
are somehow suppressed and of course
suppressor should be punished and that's
how they see the situation that if I'm
suppressed and my speech and my rights
are suppressed then why should you get
to speak that that is how I see it. I
might be wrong. I honestly don't think
that Charlie Kirk situation was this
particular situation. I think there's
much more involved in here than just
transgender person that didn't like
Charlie. I don't think that Charlie
Crook was uh killed because he
challenged certain um ideologies or
challenged certain culture in the in the
country. I think he was killed because
he was very effective.
>> Well, you know, this is something that I
think is revoly for a lot of Americans.
I I happened to be at a lunch today. Uh
a a lunch that included three former
congressmen and a bunch of professors.
And I was shocked at how many of them,
especially people that would identify as
Democrats, had never heard of Charlie
Kirk. I was sitting next to one and and
he kept saying, "I I don't know who this
guy is. I never heard of him."
>> And um
>> generational
>> and I was going to ask that. Now,
another friend of mine who uh is very
political but also very conservative uh
texted me last night and said that that
he believes that Charlie Kirk will go
down in history as a Martin Luther King
type figure for conservatives between
the ages of 17 and 30. I can see that
happening most definitely.
>> Do you?
>> I mean, you know, President Trump called
him a legend.
>> Yeah. President Trump thinks that that's
going to be the case. Now, I'm not
someone who followed Charlie uh that
closely uh because I'm already, you
know, in this category where I'm not
very red or blue or I'm somewhere in the
middle and you like I'm a common sense
person and I don't really follow these
rallies or anything, but I know one
thing that Charlie Kirk was definitely
crucial for President Trump. uh when it
gets to younger generation, President
Trump would not have the support of
young generation if not for Charlie K.
And that's not my opinion. That's the
number.
>> No, that's fact. That's fact. I agree
completely.
>> Right,
>> Elizabeth? I was thinking about writing
an op-ed about political assassinations
in the United States today because of
the Charlie Kirk murder. And so I went
to chat GPT to get some of the
background and I said, "Give me uh
information. Give me a list of
politically motivated assassinations or
attempted assassinations in the United
States over the last 20 years." There
were there were too many to to list. I
mean, this just a partial list. There
were too many. And a lot of them get
coverage for a day or two days because
we're talking about people like the head
of the Arkansas Democratic Party or, you
know, some some free speech uh activist
or the the former speaker of the house
of Minnesota or whatever, a gun rights
uh activist.
Charlie Kirk is different.
Already we're hearing in the media
parallels between 2025 and 1968 when
Martin Luther King was killed and two
weeks later two months later rather uh
Robert Kennedy was killed and and people
were in the streets with guns and and it
was hideous.
Are we are we looking at that kind of a
situation again now? And if so, how do
we dial it back?
>> Honestly, John, I don't know. I I've
been asking that question for a while
now. And how do we dial it back? We dial
it back by having honest media members
because this is all coming from us from
media and not like particularly me or
you. That's what we are trying to change
here me and you. But I mean look at the
big media like this is all coming from
there. And I I don't see a solution
other than educating our journalists,
our talk show hosts what the truth is,
how to filter the truth from [__]
Uh maybe educate them about when certain
agencies come out and tell you something
is this way and cannot provide proof
that they are right about this. Maybe
this is where you kind of put your
investigative skill to use and maybe
double check if they are lying or not
and get the uh get the society as much
truth as possible. But I think that's
that's what needs to happen. But like I
said, I I feel like I don't know, Joe,
like I feel like Charlie Kirk's case is
slightly a little bit different. Um I
mean I did you see the did you see the
picture of the possible shooter? They
really
>> Yes, they've really enhanced the
daylights out of this picture. There's
no way. I'm going to go on record.
There's no possible way this kid can get
away. There's no way. We have pictures
of him now, good pictures. They
recovered the weapon. His DNA is all
over it,
>> right?
>> It's just a matter of somebody
recognizing the picture and making a
phone call.
>> I think the last picture they showed, it
looks like a man, just a scrawny little
man, but I don't think he's a he's a
kid. I don't
>> Well, the the FBI is saying a
collegeaged shooter.
>> Wow. College.
>> I shouldn't say kid, but I'm 60. I'm 61.
>> Could be.
>> You know, I mean, looking at that
picture, the first thing that I thought,
and I could be wrong. I don't know.
Maybe a special ops guy can help me
here, but you know, I I have felt a high
powered rifle in my hands, and I'm sure
you have too. And
>> many times.
>> Yeah. And I think it's pretty damn
heavy. At least it was was for me. But
this was a 306 hunting rifle,
>> right?
>> It only held five rounds bolt action.
>> Um, at 200 yard with a scope or even
with with iron sights, this is a
especially when your target's just
sitting in a chair,
>> this is this is a doable shot, which
makes it even more
>> definitely a doable shot. I'm not saying
it's not. It's just, you know, the the
way it was done with one shot and
exactly in the artery knowing that the
victim is not going to survive. I don't
know. Like I
>> Yeah,
>> college kid.
>> Although you have to ask, was he aiming
at the head? Was he aiming at the chest?
The the bullets on on a on a 30 odd six,
the bullets are heavy and so they're
going to arc down.
>> Um I I I don't know. I'm speculating.
I'm wondering if it was a lucky shot.
Yeah, that's all we can do. I know that
you're pressed for time. I want to ask
you another question, and this is about
media coverage. You've spent your entire
adult life in media.
>> Yesterday, well, this morning, MSNBC
fired Matthew Dow. Um, Matthew Dow is a
former George W. Bush White House
official. He became a Democrat, ran for
Lieutenant Governor of Texas, was
defeated, and then went to MSNBC. He's
been there for quite some time. He made
two asinine statements yesterday during
the course of speculation immediately
after Charlie was was shot. First he
said, "Well, the shooter could have been
a supporter of Charlie Kirk firing into
the air um in uh in with excitement
about being, you know, near Charlie Kirk
like this is Baghdad in in 1989. You
just shoot into the air." That was a
ridiculous and stupid thing to say. Two
hours later,
he blamed Charlie for the shooting,
saying, "Well, when you go out there and
you say these provocative things and you
piss people off, what do you think is
going to happen?"
>> You're right.
>> Almost immediately, MSNBC's president
had to issue an apology and a
retraction.
Uh, Matthew Dow later issued an apology
and this morning he was fired. Now, on
the left, they're saying, "Well, what
about when Paul Pelosi was attacked?"
Uh, Fox News for days said, "Oh, this
was a lover's spat with his homosexual
lover, and they got into this fight, and
the guy hit him with a hammer." No, he
was a right-wing nut who broke into the
house and tried to beat him to death
with a hammer. Why are we so far apart
from each other in the media? And is it
possible to bring the two extremes
closer to the center?
>> Everything is possible, John. And I
think Charlie Kirk's legacy was just
that. Then you can't be fired because
you bler stupid [__] on TV. Like you
can't it's it's not right to do so. I
think if Charlie was alive, he would
actually protected the guy and said
like, "Hey, he's got the
>> I think he would."
>> Yeah. And they his constitutional right
>> allows him to do that. I mean, I can
give you my example that many people
might not like, but I mean, you know how
many people Lindsey Graham pisses off on
daily basis?
>> You know what I mean? Lindsey Graham has
He's right.
>> I'm I'm guilty. I'm guilty of doing
that.
>> Me, too. And if, God forbid something
happened to Lindsey Graham, I'm not
going to blame Lindsey Graham for
getting shot somewhere. You know what I
mean? He's he's a despicable human
being, but he's got he's got rights.
He's got rights. And and I don't think
that it's it's it's a correct action to
fire people that say something we don't
like. Again, that was Charlie's um
entire legacy that this country should
uphold um its constitution. And coming
from a ex-s Soviet country as I come
from, this means a whole lot of big deal
for me. like this is this is very
important for me and I take this very
seriously because I know what happens in
the nation when your free speech
>> is um in some shape or form restricted
and I know what it leads to and it's
it's it's a disaster. So
>> yes indeed. Yes indeed. Elizabeth, uh
tell us where people can see more of
your work, watch your TV appearances.
What are you doing these days?
>> Absolutely. Well, I'm for um I I'm a
journalist for Unified TV, but they can
also find me on Instagram. They can also
find me on X. Um but highly recommended
uh Unifi TV 800 plus shows.
>> Fantastic. Elizabeth Lane, thanks very
much for joining us. Elizabeth is an
investigative journalist. She's a
producer and documentary filmmaker. Find
her work both on Instagram and at
Unified Television. And again, she just
happened to be in proximity to the
hospital. She finally got into the
hospital in Orin, Utah when Charlie Kirk
died yesterday. Thanks for being with
us, Elizabeth.
>> Thank you so much, John.